Miguel Xochicale

Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging School of Biomedical Engineering and Imaging Sciences Department of Biomedical Engineering

> King's College London, UK ■ miguel.xochicale@kcl.ac.uk

★ http://mxochicale.github.io/ · m mxochicale

Research Interests

My research interests are in real-time and automatic signal and image processing techniques and AI-based fetal biomechanics. I have also experience in areas of Human-Robot Interaction, Movement Variability, Wearables in Medicine, Ultrasound-Guided Interventions, Medical Robotics, and Research Software Engineering. I have passion for real-time AI-based technologies for Healthcare.

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Engineering

Birmingham, UK

The University of Birmingham

Nov 2014 - Nov 2018

Thesis: Nonlinear Analysis to Quantify Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Interaction.

Supervisors: Professor Chris Baber and Professor Martin Russell

Thesis submission: 26/10/2018. Passed Viva: 11/01/2019. Awarded PhD degree: 12/07/2019.

Links: Thesis: 🚨 Github: 🖶 Website: 🗹

M.Sc. in Signal Processing

Puebla, México Sep 2004 – Sep 2006

Institute of Astrophysics, Optics and Electronics (INAOE) Thesis: Design of digital filters with fewer multipliers

Supervisor: Dr. Gordana Jovanovic Dolecek

Links: Thesis: 🔁 Github: 🐱

Professional Experience

King's College London Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging

London, UK

Sep 2021 - Present

- PIs: Dr Andrew King and Dr. Alberto Gomez
- I am scientifically contributing to automatic biometric recognition of Electrocardiography ultrasound data using real-time deep learning techniques and frameworks with Python-based and Qt programming languages via GitHub. Additionally, I am leading the preparation of one proceeding and one manuscript in the area of medical imaging with real-time deep learning techniques. All previous activities in collaboration with renowned clinicians and engineers in KCL, University of Oxford and University of Melbourne. See more at ().

King's College London Research Associate in Software and Hardware Engineering

London, UK *Apr 2019 – Aug 2021*

- PIs: Prof. Tom Vercauteren and Dr. Wenfeng Xia
- I pushed forward the state-of-the-art of Ultrasound-Guidance Interventions where was involved in the development of a needle tip tracking system, real-time ultrasound image processing, quality management system (QMS) for clinical translation of medical devices, and public engagement activities. Similarly, I developed validation experiments with linear stages under Windows and GNU/Linux OSs, designed electronic PCBs and design CAD pieces for 3D printing holders, characterised ultrasonic transducers, operate clinical ultrasound devices and contributing to a Python library via GitHub following QMS. All the previous activities in collaboration with an amazing team of renowned clinicians, engineers, QMS specialists and researchers in KCL and UCL. Additionally, I lead the preparation of one manuscript in a high-impact factor journal. See more at (\$\overline{L}^2\$).

INAOE's Robotics Laboratory Research Assistant in Robotics

Puebla, México Feb 2013 – Aug 2013

- Advisor: Dr. Angélica Muñoz Meléndez
- I developed a Human-Robot Interaction application for dancing activities based on a Patrolbot mobile robot and a single three-axial accelerometer. (See documents and code: 🗹).

Madero University Teaching Lecturer in Mechatronic Engineering

Puebla, México Jan 2012 – Jan 2013

- I proposed and supervised the following students projects: Haptic Referee Glove, Lightmetre and Pychometre Sensors, Smart Irrigation, Persistent Of Vision Bicycle Wheel and a Delta Robot Structure (See documents and code:
- I proposed and designed a Mechatronic Laboratory which includes: (i) a benchmark for laboratories in mechatronics in México and Puebla, (ii) a 3D layout design and (iii) minimal requirements of hardware and software for the laboratory (See documents and layout: 🗷).

INAOE Research Internship in Robotics Puebla, México Sep 2003 – Mar 2004

• I implemented a speed control for a two-degree-of-freedom robot with microcontrollers PIC 16F84 & 16F877 which communicated via RS-232 to LabVIEW's Virtual Instruments.

Teaching and Supervision Experience

King's College London Supervision	London, UK Jan 2020 – Present
Student: Tsz Yan (Goosie) Leung MSc student in Medical Engineering and Physics (Clinical Engineering) Title: "Towards simple and effective ultrasound-guidance procedures" Co-supervisors: A. King and A. Gomez	Feb 2021 – Aug 2022
Student: Thea Bautista M. Eng. in Biomedical Engingeering Title: GAN-based synthetic ultrasound imaging for fetal development Co-supervisors: H. Kerdegari, L. Peralta-Pereira, and R. Aughwane	Oct 2021 – May 2022
Student: Guilherme Gomes de Figueiredo Summer Project: synthetic ultrasound imagining with AI	Jun 2021 – Aug 2021
Student: Amal Hussein Summer Project: Ultrasound-guidance simulator	Jun 2021 – Aug 2021
Student: Alexander Mitton M.Sc. Project: Vibro-tactile stimulator for dystonia research Co-supervisors: C. Bergeles, V. Mcclelland and A. Worley	Jan 2020 – Sep 2020
Teaching Associate	Jan 2020 – Present
 Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Alejandro Granados Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Hongbin Liu Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Christos Bergeles 	Jan 2022 – Apr 2022 Jan 2021 – Apr 2021 Jan 2020 – Apr 2020
The University of Birmingham Teaching Associate	Birmingham, UK Aug 2014 – Apr 2018
 Engineering Maths 2. Lecturers: Prof. Martin Russell, Dr Carl Anthony Engineering Maths 2. Lecturer: Prof. Martin Russell Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu Matlab Laboratories. Lecturer: Dr Edward Tarte Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu Small Embedded Systems. Lecturer: Prof. Chris Baber 	Jan 2018 – Apr2018 Aug 2017 – Dec 2017 Aug 2017 – Dec 2017 Jan 2017 – Apr 2017 Aug 2016 – Dec 2016 Aug 2016 – Dec 2016
Supervision	Jun 2018 – Dec 2018
Student: Dinghuang Zhang M.Sc. Project: Tools for Human-Humanoid Collaboration Co-supervisor: Chris Baber.	
Bilingual Hight School TECMilenio University	Puebla, México

Teaching Associate

Universidad Madero

Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng.

• Information Technology ${\bf Z}$, Euclidean Geometry ${\bf Z}$, and Microsoft Office Access ${\bf Z}$

Aug 2013 - Dec 2013

Jan 2012 - Dec 2012

Puebla, México

• Fundamentals of Automation 🗹, Industrial Electronics 🖸, Research Projects 🖸, Metrology 🖸, Physics 🖸, and Computer Integrating Manufacturing, and Power Electronics

Universidad Iberoamericana Puebla Teaching Associate in Electronic Eng.

Puebla, México Jan 2007 – Dec 2011

• Stochastic Processes **(Z')**, Digital Signal Processing **(Z')**, and Analog Filters.

Instituto Tecnológico Superior de Atlixco Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng.

Puebla, México Aug 2006 – Jun 2007

- (01/2007 06/2007) Electronics I, Numerical Methods, and Electricity and Magnetism.
- (08/2006 12/2006) Electricity and Magnetism, and Electricity and Industrial Electronics

Publications

- 1. B.-P. Antonio, D. Badillo-Perez, D. Coyotzi-Molina, D. Cruz, R. Montenegro, L. Vazquez, and **M. Xochicale**, "Piloting diversity and inclusion workshops in artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in *17th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '22)*, Mar. 2022.
- 2. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Nonlinear methods to quantify movement variability in human-humanoid interaction activities," Mar. 2021. arXiv: 1810.09249 [eess.SP], Full Manuscript.
- 3. R. Montenegro, E. Corona, D. Badillo-Perez, A. Mandujano, L. Vazquez, D. Cruz, and **M. Xochicale**, "Air4children: Artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in *16th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '21)*, Feb. 2021. arXiv: 2103.07637 [cs.R0].
- 4. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability in human-humanoid imitation activities," in *5th International Conference on Human Agent Interaction (HAI '17)*, Bielefeld, Germany, Oct. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 5. **M. Xochicale**, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Towards the quantification of human-robot imitation using wearable inertial sensors," in 12th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '17), Vienna, Austria, Mar. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 6. **M. Xochicale**, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Analysis of the movement variability in dance activities using wearable sensors," in *2nd International Symposium on Wearable Robotics* (*WeRob '16*), Segovia, Spain, Oct. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 7. **M. Xochicale**, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Understanding movement variability of simplistic gestures using an inertial sensor," in 5th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays (PerDis '16), Oulu, Finland, Jun. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 8. **M. Xochicale** and G. Jovanovic-Dolecek, "A new method for design narrow band lowpass fir filters using a scale function," in *2nd International Conference on Electronic Design (ICED '06)*, Veracruz, Mexico, Nov. 2006, Conference Paper.

Posters

- 1. **M. Xochicale**, "Open-cortex: A continuous integration framework for open scientific communication," in 1st Conference on Reproducibility, Replicability and Trust in Science (RRTS '20), Cambridge, England (Virtual Conference), Sep. 2020, Poster Abstract.
- 2. **M. Xochicale**, "Quantification of dynamic facial expressions with shannon entropy in human-humanoid interaction," in 1st Symposium on Machine Learning and Dynamical Systems (MLDS '19), London, UK, Feb. 2019, Poster Abstract.

Talks

- 1. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Nonlinear analysis to quantify human movement variability from time-series data," in *neuromatch* 3.0 (*NMC3 '20*), Virtual Conference, Oct. 2020, Presentation Abstract.
- M. Xochicale, "Quantifying movement variability with nonlinear dynamics for human-humanoid interaction," in 25th International Conference on Difference Equations and Applications (ICDEA '19), London, UK, Jun. 2019, Slices abstract.
- 3. **M. Xochicale**, "Quantifying the inherent chaos of human movement variability," in 15th Experimental Chaos and Complexity Conference (ECCC '18), Madrid, Spain, Jun. 2018, Presentation Abstract.
- 4. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability for facial expressions with nonlinear dynamics," in 7th Consortium of European Research on Emotion Conference (CERE '18), Glasgow, Scotland, UK, Apr. 2018, Presentation abstract.

Grants, Awards and Honours

- King's Public Engagement grant for the project "FETUS: Finding a fETus with an Ultrasound Simulator" led by myself and in collaboration with Fang-Yu Lin and Shu Wang (07/01/2021 07/01/2022)
- Alexander Mitton won the Outstanding Individual Project award for his M.Sc. project, which I was the main supervisor, on designing a wearable, vibrotactile stimulation device for patients with dystonia (15/10/2020)

- King's Health Partners grant for the project "Sensory system abnormalities in childhood dystonia" lead by Verity McClelland and in collaboration with Carlos Seneci (14/04/2020 9/06/2020)
- My work "Towards Healthy Ageing with Humanoid Robots" was selected for a talk at the second forum of Mexican Talent, Innovation Match MX 2017, 🗗 🖟 🛗 11/01/2017
- I won the best poster award at the XIV Symposium of Mexican Students in the UK at University of Edinburgh \(\mathbb{L} \) \(\mathbb{I} \) \(\text{6-18/06/2016} \)
- My project of a low-cost robot was selected among 125 applications received from 35 countries and presented at the first international public entrepreneurship program in Mexico (MECATE 2015).

 20-24/07/2015
- Ph.D. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology. 11/2014-11/2018
- Markovito's team won the first place at the Mexican Tournament of Robotics 2013 in the category at HOME where I presented a Human-Robot Interaction Dance Demo. 25-27/05/2013
- M.Sc. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology. 09/2004-09/2006

Skills

Programming Python[2014-present], R[2013-present], Robot Operating System (ROS)[2016-present], GNU-Octave (or MatLab)[2009-present], LaTeX[2006-present], C and C++[2015-present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016-present], pandoc[2017-present], open-source enthusiast at GitHub (@mxochicale)[2015-present], and continuous integration and continuous delivery [2019-present].

Tools GNU/Linux Operating System user (e.g. OpenSuse, Debian and Ubuntu)[2005-present] Single-board computers and microcontrollers (e.g. NVIDIA Jetson Nano, RaspberryPi, BeagleBone, Arduino and PIC)[2010-present], Inertial Measurement Units (e.g. calibration, collection and data analysis)[2013-present], Web design (e.g. Github pages, Jekyll)[2015-present], and Graphic design (e.g. Inkscape, GIMP)[2014-present], CAD design (e.g. Autodesk invetor, blender, FreeCAD)[2015-present], Artificial Neural Networks (e.g. PyTorch, and TensorFlow)[2017-present], 3D printing (e.g., flsun, cura) [2019-present], Video framegrabbers (e.g. PCI and usb from ephipan), and Medical imaging (e.g. 3D slicer, ITK-SNAP).

Languages Spanish[Native], English[Fluent] and interested in learning Chinese.

Extra Activities

King's College London Outreach activities and scientific engagement London, UK

10-11-2021

reach activities and scientific engagement Sep 2019 – Present

Organising events at the Early Career Researcher Network of the BMEIS
 Participation in the Westminster Enterprise Week to engage students aged 14-18 to Biomedical Engineering

- Participant in the STEAM WEEK organised by the City Westminster Council to engage students aged 14-18 to STEAM

 23-03-2021
- Alexandra Lautarescu and I organised the Reproducible, Interpretable, Open, & Transparent Science Club at St Thomas' Hospital
 02-2020 – 06-2020
- For the event In2ScienceUK, I shared my scientific journey to young scientist on how they can become better scientist.

 20-08-2019
- For the New Scientist Live, I showcased software that helps doctors to create 3D models of brain tumors using AI. 09-2019

University of Birmingham Outreach activities and scientific engagement

Birmingham, UK Aug 2014 – Jun 2018

• Finalist at the Three Minute Thesis Competition 2018. Video: and GitHub: 505-2018

• Research Poster Conference for (2015) 🖾, (2016) 🖾, and (2018) 🖾. GitHub: 🖝.

• Demoing Human-Robot Activities at the Undergraduate Open Days. GitHub: 🖶. 2014–2018

• Coordinator of the Science Seminars for the Mexican Society. GitHub: , Website: . 2017–2018

AIR4Children México & UK

- Building Artificial Intelligence and Robotics for Children (air4children) with the purpose of teaching AIR to children for free. Twitter: **y**@air4children GitHub: **⋈**@air4children 2019–Present
- Creation Libre Robotics, a non-profit organization aiming to freely transfer knowledge in Robotics to Mexican children. Website:

 2013 − 2017

Developer of the Website "Machine Learning for México"

México & UK

• GitHub: ➡, Website: ☑ 2013 – 2018